Today's דף daf *daf* is דף daf; ל"ו *daf lamed vav*, we
start on ל"ה עמוד amud ב' *lamed hey amud bet* and let's
take a look. Wait,
what we're, אביי הוה יתיב *Abaye hava yativ*, two lines from the
top of ל"ה עמוד ב' *lamed hey amud bet*, so we're about
an עמוד *amud* behind, let's see if we can catch up. אביי
הוה יתיב קמיה דרב יוסף *Abaye hava yativ kamei d'Rav Yosef*, אביי
*Abaye* was sitting in front of רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, איפסיקא ליה
רצועה Retzuah. דתפילין *isktei retzuah d'tefillin*, his רצועה Ritzua. *retzuah* broke. Now
remember so far we said that the black of the תפילין Tefillin
*tefillin* is הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai. *halacha l'moshe misinai*. Now
we're going to talk about other aspects of the black of the
רצועה retzuah *retzuah*. Anyway, his רצועה retzuah *retzuah* broke. אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, so he said to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, מהו למקטריה *mahu
lemiktarei*, can I knot it? Can I fix my strap by knotting
the broken halves together? אמר ליה *Amar lei*, וקשרתם u’kshartam, *u'kshartem* כתיב
*ksiv*. It says you shall bind it, שתהא קשירה keshira, תמה *shetihyeh
kshirah tamah*. It should be a perfect unbroken binding, which presumably means
that the strap used for binding cannot be broken. It has to
be a whole
strap, or maybe there can only be the one knot, but no,
you cannot bind your strap. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף
לרב אשי *Amar lei Rav Acha brei d'Rav Yosef l'Rav Ashi*, he
said to רב אשי Rav Ashi *Rav Ashi*, מהו למתפריה דאיילי לטיפיי
לגאו *mahu lemitfrei d'ayiley l'tifey legav*, how about not knotting the break
but how about sewing and putting the sewing, the stitches, on the
inside? So if somebody finds you, someone looks at the outside, they
won't see the stitching. That makes it look a lot better, that's
a real fix. אמר *Amar*, so he said, פוק חזי Puk Chazi,
מאי עמא דבר *puk chazi mai ama devar*. Go see what the
people are doing. Which
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says means, and since people don't do it, it's
אסור *assur*. And which תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says means, and since people
do it, it's מותר
*mutar*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* assumes that פוק חזי מאי עמא דבר *puk
chazi mai ama devar* is usually used in a קולא *kula* context,
so that's why he chooses to read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that
way. Mike, you're right, how often does this happen for us anyway?
But you have to remember we use עור בהמה גסה *or behemah
gassah*. We use thick leather as opposed to thin leather which would
tear easier. We also use thick straps as opposed to very thin
straps. But right, how often do you see it anyway? Also problem
of following common practice if it's something that you don't observe, so
what is there to follow? Like if רש"י Rashi *Rashi* would say,
well nobody ever does it, maybe the reason nobody ever does it
is because it doesn't happen. Right, you can only bring evidence if
the circumstance happens how they deal with it.
Okay, because if it's truly done well and you can't tell by
looking at the outside, you would not know.
Right,
exactly. All right, so anyway that's that, that's about the strap breaking.
But now we're also going to talk about the length of the
straps, the proper length. Let's take a look. רב פפא *Rav Pappa*.
Is it for the ראש rosh *rosh* or the יד Yad *yad*?
Not clear, presumably either, but we'll try, it'll be a little bit
clearer maybe in a minute. Okay, אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*,
גרדומי Gardumey רצועות ritzuyos כשרות *gardumei retzuot kesherot*. The remnant of the
straps is sufficient. The phrase גרדומים *gardumim* basically means that we assume
that there's a requisite length to begin with, but even though you
had that requisite length to begin with, if you're left with a
little remnant of it at the end, you're okay. We have that
idea by ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzit*. By, like there's a certain length that
the string of the ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzit* has to be to start
with, but if after you made your ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzit* it tore
and there's a little bit left, it's still okay. So he said
when it comes by תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*, that's כשר Kosher *kasher*.
Meaning like mending your shoes?
No, no, no, we're talking about is your תפילין Tefillin *tefillin* still
כשר Kasher *kasher*? My תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*, let's say we say the
length of the strap it has to go down to your waist
for the של ראש Shel Rosh. *shel rosh*, let's say. We'll talk
about it in a minute. So you did that, but then what
happened was it ripped. We're back to it ripping. So he's saying
if it's okay if you have a little bit less here of
the strap since it started at the right length. We're talking about
the תפילין Tefillin *tefillin* are still כשר Kasher *kasher*.
You're not, let's say you're making the תפילין Tefillin. *tefillin* and you
definitely make this thick תפילין Tefillin *tefillin* and you have a little
leftover, can you?
No, that's not that discussion at all. I know, it's not that
discussion. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ולאו מילתא היא *v'lav
milta hi*, that's not correct. מדאמרי בני רבי חייא *mi'da'amru bnei Rebbi
Chiya*, since the sons of רבי חייא *Rebbi Chiya* said, גרדומי תכלת
וגרדומי אזוב כשרים *gardumei techelet v'gardumei ezov kesherim*,
that if you have your תכלת *techelet* here is a stand-in for
all of ציצית Tzitzis *tzitzit*, but obviously refers to the blue of
ציצית tzitzis. *tzitzit*, so if that string broke and there's a tiny
bit left it's okay. And similarly if the אזוב *ezov*, you know
the hyssop that you do the dipping in for פרה אדומה *parah
adumah* or for the מצורע *metzorah*, if that started at a requisite
length and then it broke and you only have a little bit
left, that's okay. So that's what they taught, that there the גרדומים
*gardumim*, the remnant, is okay.
התם הוא דתשמישי מצוה Mitzvah נינהו *Hatam hu de'tashmishei mitzvah ninhu*.
That's true over there, where those things, and this is extremely important
introducing two categories of things used for מצוות mitzvot *mitzvot*. There it's
true that we should be more lenient because those are things that
serve the מצוה Mitzvah. *mitzvah*. אבל הכא דתשמישי קדושה Kedusha נינהו לא
*Aval hacha de'tashmishei kedusha ninhu lo*. But here where these are things
that are called תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei Kedusha. *tashmishei kedusha*, we would not
be as lenient. What is the difference? You know what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* calls תשמישי מצוה Tashmishe Mitzvah *tashmishei mitzvah*, we would more
call like מצוה Mitzvah, *mitzvah* objects. So things like a ציצית tzitzis,
*tzitzit*, a לולב Lulav *lulav*, a שופר *shofar*, those are תשמישי מצוה
Tashmishe Mitzvah, *tashmishei mitzvah*, מצוה Mitzvah, *mitzvah* objects, and they have certain
requirements but they don't really have
any.
Now okay, I don't know what's going on. Now we seem to
be okay.
Anyway, so those things are mitzvah objects. Mitzvah objects don't have intrinsic
קדושה, Kedusha they have because they're used to do a מצוה Mitzvah
that they're significant and therefore the primary laws that govern their use,
you know, in terms of the respect you show them, is during
the period of the מצוה. Mitzvah After the period of the מצוה,
Mitzvah like you know what do you do with your לולב Lulav
afterwards? So you're not supposed to throw it out in your trash,
but basically you can wrap it in a plastic bag and just
dispose of it in a disrespectful way. That we try to use
them for doing another מצוה, Mitzvah so you know the whole idea
of like using your leftover
לולב Lulav for making
for for the
fire for making מצות, Matzos, or I don't know burning their oh
burning their חמץ. Chametz. Anyway, that's what you try to do with
it. But מעיקר הדין, Me'ikar Hadin, once the מצוה Mitzvah is done,
you know, it's basically there are no real laws that govern it
and even during the time, the amount of respect that or you
know sort of laws that define its use are not so weighty.
That's as opposed to תשמישי מצוה—תשמישי קדושה. kedusha תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei Kedusha
are things that are associated basically with כתבי הקודש Kitvei Hakodesh or
maybe a little more specifically שם השם Shem Hashem and therefore those
things because of the association with שם השם Shem Hashem and כתבי
הקודש, Kitvei Hakodesh, those things have a much higher level of קדושה
kedusha and that's not just when the מצוה Mitzvah is being used,
that's a status that's just intrinsically associated with it. It's why it
stops being usable, you put it into שמות Sheimos and all those
types of things. You never put your לולב Lulav, into שמות. Sheimos.
That's תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishei Kedusha. So תפילין Tefillin are תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishei
Kedusha. Why? Not because you do a מצוה mitzvah with it, from
that angle they're תשמישי...
Guys, I don't know what's going on with your audio. We've been
having some internet problems today, I don't know. Anyway, so from that
perspective, we'll see if this
makes
this any better.
But let's say of a ספר תורה Sefer Torah. that you know
that had too many mistakes from the very beginning, would that still
be a תשמישי קדושה? Tashmishei Kedusha?
Yeah, I think so.
So it's not even if
it was
used, it has
to be like משמש meshamesh something?
No
no no, yeah although pick up, pick up, pick up, he's a
better expert than me. Alright, I hope it's better everybody. You know
what? I'm going to stop this and start it again. Okay. Alright,
I don't know.
Tell me if it's any better.
If of all the
logistics you ever get a שיעור Shiur started, of course
you need a CTO.
I need a שמש Shammas is what I need. Alright, anyway so
that's תשמישי מצוה, Tashmishe Mitzvah, תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishei Kedusha. What was your
question? Yeah, it doesn't matter that it was a כשר ספר תורה.
sefer torah? It matters that it was a verse, there was שם
השם, Shem Hashem, and so on. That תפילין Tefillin are תשמישי מצוה,
Tashmishe Mitzvah you use them to do a מצוה Mitzvah, with, but
they also are תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei Kedusha because they're connected to the
קלפים Klafim on the inside. An interesting point that I'll get to
in a minute is what is the status of the בית Bayis
itself with the ש Shin on it of the של ראש.
Shel Rosh, Oh, you said we're looking at a משנה Mishnah yesterday.
Yeah, well as a side,
so תוספות Tosafos says that that של ראש, Shel Rosh, that might
be because it's connected to a ש Shin which is part of
שם השם. Shem Hashem. That might not just be תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei
Kedusha, that might be actual קדושה kedusha, itself, like כתבי הקודש Kitvei
Hakodesh or something—something that has שם השם Shem Hashem on it. It's
not just serving the קלפים Klafim on the inside. We wouldn't call
the קלפים Klafim תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei Kedusha, we would call them כתבי
הקודש. Kitvei Hakodesh. Anyway, we'll get to that in a minute.
So going back to this, the גמרא Gemara says look, now here's
an interesting thing. Normally we assume the difference between תשמישי מצוה Tashmishe
Mitzvah. and תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei Kedusha are like what type of a
respect you have to show the object, and you know שמות Sheimos
and those types of questions. But here the גמרא Gemara says since
ציצית tzitzit are תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei Kedusha, if they break, you can
be יוצא Yotzei with a little bit. But since תפילין Tefillin are
תשמישי... I'm sorry, ציצית tzitzit are תשמישי מצוה. Tashmishe Mitzvah. Since תפילין
Tefillin are תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei Kedusha, we're going to assume weightier requirements
and we're going to assume you need the full length of the
רצועה. It's not good if it broke and a little is left
over, which personally I don't understand at all because first of all
we're looking at the תפילין Tefillin, from its role as תשמישי מצוה.
Tashmishe Mitzvah We're not asking do I have to put it in
שמות, Sheimos, we're asking can I be יוצא Yotzei the מצוה mitzvah
of תפילין. tefillin So what we're looking at it from its dimension
of תשמישי מצוה Tashmishey Mitzvah. number one, and number two even if
it is תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei Kedusha, it's not exactly clear to me
why that should be the higher criteria, you know. So I'm not
exactly sure the logic that the גמרא Gemara is making here but
it is saying that because it is תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei Kedusha, therefore
a remnant is not enough. The only thing I can maybe imagine
and maybe this is what sort of Michael was thinking about before
is that maybe because if there is a law of like שמות...
Sheimos... to the תפילין tefillin part, right? And let's say the תפילין
tefillin straps do break, what do you do with it? You put
it in שמות, Shaimos, right? Because they were תשמישי מצוה. Tashmishey Mitzvah,
So maybe because the idea of something sort of being broken off
is more of a problem, right? It's not like if if you're,
you know, if the bottom part of your לולב, Lulav let's say
you rip off a לולב lulav leaf, you know, what do you
do with it? You can put it in the garbage. It's no
longer serving its מצוה mitzvah. purpose. So the fact that something broke
off is not so much a problem, then it stops being associated.
Here, the sense of it belongs there and it's taken away from
it by the תפילין tefillin strap is higher because of the concept
as תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishey Kedusha. So maybe that makes the issue of
גרדומי more problematic as well. Not clear to me, but that's how
the גמרא Gemara concludes and therefore breaking the תפילין tefillin strap is
is not going to be good. You need the full length. Yes.
So, I guess so the case is, I'm just trying to understand
this, is let's say it needs to be a foot long and
now you only have an inch long, right? Let's say it was
a foot long, you made it two feet long, now what happened?
No, no, no. It's only when it goes
less than the initial שיעור. Shiur. We don't know yet what the
initial שיעור Shiur is. גרדומין Gardumin is it started the right way
and now it's less than the initial.
The minimum.
Correct. But we don't know yet what that minimal שיעור Shiur is.
So let's take a look. But it was more than the הלכה
Halacha by ציצית because when your ציצית tear they can still be
כשר even if they weren't כשר that way if you had made
them that way initially.
But if it was more and now it's the right שיעור, Shiur,
you're no problem? Yes, exactly. Exactly. It's not a matter of like
if it doesn't look as nice anymore. Correct. Correct. It seems like
that was an issue, you
know, but not here, not here. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, it's only there by like ציצית which is תשמישי מצוה, tashmishei
mitzvah. not here by תפילין tefillin which is תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishey Kedusha.
So the גמרא Gemara says בכלל, Bichlal, so okay, from this whole
discussion I accept that גרדומין Gardumin is not good, but from this
discussion I can infer דאית להו שיעורא, De-is Lehu Shiura, that there
is a minimum size of the length of the רצועה. דכמה שיעורייהו,
De-kama Shiyurayhu, what is its minimum, what is its שיעור? Shiur? אמר
רמי בר חמא אמר ריש לקיש Amar Rami Bar Chama Amar Resh
Lakish עד אצבע צרדה Ad Etzba Tzerada until your אצבע צרדה Etzba
Tzerada which רש"י Rashi says means your snapping finger, which רש"י Rashi
says means your, actually רש"י Rashi, says it means your forefinger, תוספות
Tosafos says you don't snap with your forefinger, תוספות Tosafos says it
means your middle finger. Okay, עד אצבע צרדה, Ad Etzba Tzerada, I
will say in a minute what this means. רב כהנא מחוי כפוף,
Rav Kahana Machvei Kafuf, רב כהנא Rav Kahana demonstrated, showed, like if
it were bent. רב אשי מחוי פשוט, Rav Ashi Machvei Pashut, רב
אשי Rav Ashi demonstrated as if it were straightened out. What does
this mean? So two explanations. One רש"י Rashi says means it's just
a finger length, so it's basically the length between your thumb and
your forefinger according to רש"י, Rashi according to תוספות Tosafos it would
be your thumb and your middle finger. But you know that bout
of length, that's how long it has to be presumably after the
knot of the של ראש, Shel Rosh how far it has
to go down, presumably, it's not clear.
Or maybe that point of יד yad after the ring. And that's
כפוף Kafuf which is like very widely spread and פשוט Pashut which
רש"י Rashi says like not widely spread would be like this, basically
about half size. That's one explanation, both רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos
set up, although they debate which is the finger we're talking about.
The other explanation though is which is what Mike was thinking is
no, we're talking about the של יד Shel Yad and we mean
it has to get all the way to your middle finger from
here. And that's actually how we פסקן. Pasken. And then the only
difference between כפוף Kafuf and פשוט Pashut is are we talking that
your finger is bent down? So it'll be enough to get to
like the palm of your hand? That's כפוף. Kafuf. Or are we
talking about straight and it has to get out there? And that's
basically what we rule, it has to be long enough. We make
like seven wraps, that's not really required. והלכתא? V'hilchasa? והלכתא, V'hilchasa, you
can do one wrap here and then go to your finger. But
that's how long it has to be to get after the one
sort of tightening and knot to get to your finger by the
של יד. Shel Yad. How long does the של ראש Shel Rosh
have to be if our גמרא Gemara is talking about the של
יד? Shel Yad? The גמרא Gemara, doesn't say. The שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch actually does not really say very clearly how long the של
ראש Shel Rosh, has to be. If you look at the bottom
of תוספות Tosafos, פוק חזי, תוספות Tosafos says like
this,
'וכמה שיעורייהו', V'kama Shiyurayhu, thank you.
So he says like this, 'ובשימושא רבא', U've-Shimusha Rabba,
again I have to find out more about this work. There was
this work called שימושא רבא Shimusha Rabba which they are always quoting
about in הלכות תפילין. Hilchos Tefillin. It must, I think it was
some גאוני Geonic work that had a lot there about הלכות תפילין.
Hilchos Tefillin. So near the end of this תוספות, Tosafot about six
lines before it's over, he says like this, 'ובשימושא רבא דתפילין יש
דלביש רצועה עד דמטי לחדא כנגד מילה', U've-Shimusha Rabba De-Tefillin yesh dilvish
ritzua ad d'mati le-chada k'neged mila, so here's what it says in
the שימושא רבא Shimusha Rabba in the
laws of תפילין, tefillin. דלביש רצועה עד דמטי לחדא כנגד מילה, dilvish
ritzua ad d'mati le-chada k'neged mila, so one of the רצועות retzuot
coming out from your של ראש, Shel Rosh one of them has
to reach your מילה, Mila, which basically is below the waist, מימינא,
Mi-yamina,
that's on the right hand side, וחדא כנגד הלב משמאלא, ve-chada k'neged
halev mi-smola,
and one of them has to get to your heart on the
left. תוספות Tosafot earlier quoted an opinion that on your right it
doesn't have to go all the way below the waist, it has
to get more or less to your belly button. Okay.
And then he has a discussion about how wide it is, 'עוד
יש אומר דמצות שיעור רוחב הרצועה', Od yesh omer demitzvas shiur rochav
ha-ritzua, how wide, 'יותר מכשעורה', Yoser mik'shiora, better to be wider than
a wheat grain of wheat, 'ופחות מכשעורה בצמלא' U'fachos mik'shora batzmala than
a barley grain, 'ואם יותר כשר', v'im yoser kasher, but if it's
bigger it's really not a problem.
Ours are much wider than that. Yes. Anyway, he says it's not
a problem if it's bigger. Yes, I don't know where they're getting
it from. A lot of this they're getting it from tradition. But
here it's amazing. The גמרא Gemara most of, you know, might be
talking about a של יד Shel Yad and then there's all these
weird ideas about a של ראש shel rosh, which are about this
far for the right and this far for the left. It's... It
does become an issue when the תפילין tefillin? actually does break, or
when, like we talked about yesterday, the black wears off, because if
you say that if it’s the part beyond the שיעור, shiur, it’s
not a problem. If it’s the part within the שיעור, shiur, it
is a problem. Okay, and it is quite interesting that the גמרא
Gemara, is not clear if it’s talking about a של יד, shel
yad, של ראש, shel rosh what it’s talking about, and תוספות Tosafot
is trying to fill the gap.
In the first case, yeah, for the רצועה you could leave it
there, or you would, you could cut it off before the, before
the, where it’s not black.
That’s a good point. I think it’s even not a problem. I
mean, I hear your point that maybe you can just, you know,
maybe you can just,
maybe if it’s cut off it’s not part of it, but if
it’s not cut off, but it’s still considered part of it. I
think we say that even if you don’t cut it off, if
it’s beyond the שיעור, shiur, it’s not an issue, but I’d have
to double-check that.
And make sure I want one thing, right. And you were saying
it's this long according to one way of explaining it, that’s after
you made the tie. Yeah, you make one tie and then a
little bit more on your arm, you know, that length more on
your arm after you tied it.
That after you do this,
it has to reach all the way to your navel, yeah, according
to the first explanation.
According to the second explanation, it’s
just this length after you do the tie, presumably after you do
the tie. Right. Right.
Now, I did want to say something, I’m going to cheat a
little and I know we’re behind, but I couldn’t resist because we
had discussed רש"י Rashi and רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and now you
see תוספות Tosafot also this whole question about being influenced by these
other books, שימושא רבא Shimusha Rabba and so on. The רש"י-רבינו תם
תפילין tefillin was not just רש"י Rashi, and רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam
רמב"ם’s Rambam quote says like רש"י, Rashi the ראב"ד Ra'avad critiques the
רמב"ם, Rambam, there are others, he basically positions, shows the position of
רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. You know, they’re not just, it’s רמב"ם Rambam
and ראב"ד, Ra'avad, it’s not just רש"י Rashi and רבינו תם, Rabbeinu
Tam. you know, it’s a larger issue. So there’s a famous תשובה
teshuvah that they asked the רמב"ם Rambam about
about which order you put your תפילין tefillin in, and they said,
we see what you wrote in משנה תורה, Mishneh Torah, but we
had this other tradition about הויות באמצע, Havayos Ba'emtza, you know, which
is basically רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, what should we do? And I
just want to read you one line of his answer where he
says, I made copies of it, but I’ll just read it now
quickly. He says like this, he says, it’s a really fascinating answer,
he says like this, he says, כך היה דתי מקודם ככם, Kach
haya dati mikodem kachem, I used to think like you, like רבינו
תם, Rabbeinu Tam, like הויות באמצע, Havayos Ba'emtza, ותפילין היו לי בארץ
מערב ve-tefillin hayu li be-Eretz Ma'arav
when I was still living in the West, in Spain, כך היו,
kach hayu,
those were my תפילין tefillin. that they were like רבינו תם. Rabbeinu
Tam, I mean, he’s not saying רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam. they were
הויות באמצע, Havayos Ba'emtza, וכתב כזה אשר חיבר התפילין ושמו רב משה
מקורדובה. ve-kasav kaze osher chibbar hatfillin u-shemo Rav Moshe mi-Cordova.
So this was because it was influenced by a book written about
laws of תפילין tefillin. by רב משה Rav Moshe of Cordova. Interesting,
in some in some texts of the תשובה, teshuvah, it says רב
משה בר מימון מקורדובה, Rav Moshe bar Maimon mi-Cordova, which obviously is
not true, but there was another רב משה Rav Moshe of Cordova
that wrote laws of תפילין tefillin. and people followed it and basically
it was like רבינו תם’s Rabbeinu Tam, position, it had הויות באמצע.
Havayos Ba'emtza. רמב"ם Rambam says that was my תפילין. tefillin. And he
says, ואותו החיבור הוא שהטעני והטעה כל אנשי המערב מלפני, ve-oto hachibbur
hu she-hitanu ve-hita kol anshei ha-Ma'arav milfanai,
that is what made me err and what led astray all of
the people of the West that they followed. So it shows you,
you know, the power of codes, the power of, you know, of
something that’s written and it becomes sort of the guide and the
manual and how much that influenced the practice. And then he said
even the רי Ri actually in one תשובה teshuvah indicates this idea
of הויות באמצע. Havayos Ba'emtza. And then he goes on and says,
and what how did I, what made me ultimately go back to
the other position, which, you know, we would call רש"י Rashi תפילין?
tefillin. So he says like this, for some reason this did not
collate, it’s one of those technical days. He says like this anyway,
he says a lot of גאונים, Geonim, he says like this, he
says, a lot of גאונים Geonim קלקלו דבר זה ואנשי מזרח kilkelu
davar ze ve-anshei Mizrach the people of the East, ארץ ישראל ועל
אנשי ארץ צבי Eretz Yisrael ve-al anshei Eretz Tzvi the people of
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, הקדמונים חולקים עליו. hakadmonim cholkim alav. Okay,
and now listen to this, talking about, you know, this stuff that
sounds to us very modern. Okay, he says, ואמרו לי חכמים נאמנים
כפתחו תפילין של הגאון רבינו האי ז"ל, ve-amru li chachamim ne'emanim ke-pithu
tefillin shel hagon Rabbeinu Hai zal, they opened up his תפילין tefillin
after he died presumably,
because רבינו האי Rabbeinu Hai was quoted as basically saying הויות באמצע
Havayos Ba'emtza like רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam They opened up his תפילין
tefillin ומצאו שכתובים על הסדר שאמרתי בחיבור. u-matzu she-ketuvin al haseder she-amarti
be-chibbur.
And they found that they were like what I said, it was
the normal way they’re written. And then he says, and then he
has one other line and he says like this, והראיה הברורה בדבר
זה, Ve-hara'aya habrura be-davar ze,
the proof that it’s like I’m right, that it’s the right the
way they’re written in the in the תורה, Torah, נאמר בפרק הקומץ,
ne'emar be-perek Ha-kometz, קורא על סדר התורה. koreh al seder ha-Torah.
So remember we had about קורא קורא על סדר, koreh koreh al
seder, but it ended very cryptically, oh you read it in order,
what order, in order in which way? So he had here was
the גרסא girsa that I had in the גמרא, Gemara הקורא קורא
על סדר התורה קדש לי והיה כי יביאך שמע והיה אם שמוע.
hakoreh koreh al seder ha-Torah Kadesh Li ve-Haya ki Yevi'acha Shema ve-Haya
im Shamo'a.
So when he found a נוסח nusach of the גמרא Gemara that
explicitly gave the order in the sequential order. And then he says,
ונוסח זה לא היה בספרינו בארץ מערב, ve-nusach ze lo haya be-sifreinu
be-Eretz Ma'arav,
this was not in our manuscripts in the West, in Spain, אבל
הנה מצאתי כל הנוסחאות הישנות וכך כתוב בהן. aval hinei matzati kol
hanusachot hayeshanot ve-kach katuv ba-hen. That's what's in our גמרא, Gemara right?
No,
we don’t have קדש והיה אם שמוע,
Kadesh ve-Haya
im
Shamo'a, קדש לי והיה כי יביאך, Kadesh Li ve-Haya ki Yevi'acha, no,
ימין, Yamin, שמע והיה אם שמוע משמאל.
Shema ve-Haya im Shamo'a mismol.
He had, which is very cryptic. He had the מסקנא maskana at
the end with הקורא קורא על הסדר קדש והיה כי יביאך שמע
והיה
אם שמוע.
hakoreh koreh al haseder Kadesh ve-Haya ki Yevi'acha Shema ve-Haya
im Shamo'a.
So anyway he says I found a manuscript and that's what they
do in Israel and so anyway there was an article that basically
said that they think it was because of the רמב"ם'ס Rambam's this
תשובה teshuvah again it's all speculation that totally turned the tide. Maybe
if it wasn't for this we'd all be wearing רבנו תם'ס Rabbeinu
Tam's תפילין. tefillin But if you read this תשובה teshuvah you see
it was not just like a weird opinion of רבנו תם Rabbeinu
Tam it was widespread in Spain maybe in Provence wherever he came
from they were all influenced by this one book that this רב
משה קורדובירו Rav Moshe Cordovero wrote and a lot of the גאונים
Geonim and he really turned the tide by emphasizing what his manuscripts
were רבנו האי'ס Rabbeinu Hai's תפילין. tefillin. It's fascinating if you think
about the sort of more academic things. We're going to actually look
at the ריא"ף. Riaf. Let's open up רבנו האי'ס Rabbeinu Hai's תפילין.
tfillin Let's check the manuscripts and then he said and I also
go by ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because they have stronger traditions about
תפילין. tfillin They're more מקפיד makpid about תפילין. tfillin And does that
have a lot to do with sort of turning the tide and
why now we sort of I don't know that there's an article
that speculates that it's this תשובה teshuvah that turned the tide but
it's fascinating to realize how widespread the practices were and also since
so little is from the גמרא Gemara if I'm going to write
to you here's a handbook for תפילין tfillin and you're a סופר
sofer right what are you going to do you're going to open
up two dozen pairs of תפילין tfillin and see how they're written?
No you'll use my handbook. So the influence that these handbooks could
have played and תוספות Tosafot is constantly quoting this ספר שימושא רבא.
Sefer Shimusha Rabba.
This is only twenty-four permutations and how how do we only really
have two major themes in it? We've obviously got some I go
back mostly like tenth century?
האי גאון Hai Gaon was I think tenth. He was one of
the latest גאונים. Geonim.
Yeah.
So but if there are twenty-four permutations how has it been distilled
to two? I mean because you
said that
they found a whole bunch of them in קומראן. Qumran.
Yeah so I don't know that was קומראן Qumran but once the
גמרא Gemara was there that limited the range of reasonable possibilities.
Exactly. Okay so let's continue. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay so now we have the question about about how long the
רצועות retzuot have to be. רבא קטר להו פשיט ושדי להו. Rava
katar lehu pashit v'shadi lehu. רבא Rava was קושר kosher his תפילין
tfillin and tossed it. What does tossed it mean? רש"י Rashi says
it means like he flung the רצועות retzuot. behind his back. Okay.
של
ראש shel rosh presumably right?
של ראש shel rosh yeah. רב אחא בר יעקב קטר להו ומפיטו.
Rav Acha bar Yaakov katar lehu mapitu. No he after he was
קושר kosher it he hung it meaning hung it in in front
is where he put the רצועות. retzuot
And then it says רב אחא בר יעקב אבי עבד ומר בריה
דרבינא עביד כרידן. Rav Acha bar Yaakov avi avad u'Mar brei d'Ravina
avid k'didan. And ומר בריה דרבינא Mar brei d'Ravina did like we
do which רש"י Rashi says means hung from in front. But again
this is fascinating you would think the idea that they have to
come down in front is a pretty strong הלכה. halacha. Here it
just makes it sound like it was just different practices. Some guys
did it that way some guys did it the other way and
in a way it's almost more natural that it flows behind you
just think about it like a headrest and then it like flows
behind. All right anyway so that's what you do with the straps
of the תפילין. tfillin אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב שמואל בר שילת
משמיה דרב: Amar Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Shmuel bar Shilat mishmei d'Rav:
קשר של תפילין הלכה למשה מסיני. Kesher shel tefillin halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai.
The קשר kesher that you make is הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe
mi'Sinai. Now what does this mean? How you make it? רש"י Rashi
says the fact that the של ראש shel rosh looks like a
ד' dalet and the של יד shel yad looks like a י'
yud and that forms the name of God's name ש-ד-י. Shin Dalet
Yud. רש"י Rashi says that's הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai? תוספות
Tosafot questions whether the
actual using of the רצועות to form like שם ה' Shem Hashem
if that really looks like a ד' dalet and a י' yud
and that really gives it the status of שם ה'. Shem Hashem.
But the question is what is at least
הלכה למשה מסיני?
halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai. That what? What does he say then?
קשר תפילין Kesher tefillin means he's not denying that there's a way
to make it but he's maybe denying its significance as sort of
calling it part of שם ה'. Shem Hashem.
Okay but he's saying it's still הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai Whatever there is it doesn't tell you A that
you need a קשר kesher B maybe some of the way it
looks it's not exactly clear. And by the way you should be
aware there's a big מחלוקת machloket about what the ד' dalet in
the back of the head looks like. There's your standard ד' dalet
which is somehow to make it that's shaped like a perpendicular or
whatever. And then there's something which I used to wear for many
years which is called a double ד' dalet which is two דלתי"ן
daltin like a square. If it's double ד' dalet sure if you
put two דלתי"ן daltin together it looks like a square. Why I
stopped is because it has very little basis in הלכה. halacha. It
was more like this חסידיק מנהג. Chassidic minhag. So I actually switched
it to a ד'. dalet. And the question with all of these
is are you saying that you're not יוצא yotze if you did
it the other way? At what point are we saying that it's
פסול? pasul? If it's הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai? which aspect
of it is הלכה halacha למשה מסיני? That you have it? The
base is it the shape is it the fact that it has
to be black or whatever? That is not clear. Okay אמר רב
נחמן ונויהן לבר Amar Rav Nachman v'noyeihen l'bar
and we put the the nice part on the outside which basically
means the black faces out as we sort of said before. רב
אשי הוה יתיב קמיה דמר זוטרא. Rav Ashi hava yativ kamey d'Mar
Zutra. רב אשי was in front of מר זוטרא. Mar Zutra. איתהפיך
ליה רצועה דתפילין Ithapich leh retzuah d'tefillin and his רצועה flipped the
inside part flipped on the outside. Whether it was the של ראש
shel rosh. or של יד shel yad not clear more likely it
happened on the של ראש. shel rosh. אמר ליה לא סבר ליה
מר ונויהן לבר Amar leh lo savar leh mar v'noyeihen l'bar
don't you agree that we're supposed to keep the nice part on
the outside the black part on the outside? אמר ליה לאו אדעתאי
Amar leh lav ada'atai oh thank you for pointing that out I
wasn't paying attention. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this
וראו. v'rau. So have a little דרש: drash: וראו כל עמי הארץ
כי שם השם נקרא עליך ויראו ממך. V'ra'u kol amei ha'aretz ki
shem Hashem nikra alecha v'yiru mimeka. תניא רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר אלו
תפילין שבראש. Tanya Rabbi Eliezer HaGadol omer elu tfillin she'be'rosh.
So they'll see that's the תפילין tfillin. on the ראש rosh that's
high up on the head. Now here, תוספות Tosafot just says it's
because of exactly that, that it's high up on the head, they
see it better, it's more visual than seeing somebody wearing תפילין של
ראש. tfillin shel rosh. Not only that, the גמרא Gemara says by
it says והיו לאות על ידכה, v'hayu l'os al yadecha, that the
של יד shel yad should be לך, lecha, והיו לאות, v'hayu l'os,
you know, והיה לך לאות v'hayu l'cha l'os and לא לכם לאות
lo lachem l'os and that's why we cover the של יד. shel
yad. So if the if
people are seeing you're wearing תפילין tfillin. it's focusing on the של
ראש. shel rosh. That's all makes a lot of sense. רש"י Rashi
adds to it that why it's שם השם נקרא עליך, shem Hashem
nikra alecha,
here's what רש"י Rashi says, because of the ש shin and the
ד dalet is two-thirds of שם השם. shem Hashem. And here's where
תוספות Tosafot says no, there might be a ש shin on the
תפילין tfillin but the ד dalet isn't a real ד, dalet, the
י yud isn't a real י, yud, don't start calling it שם
השם. shem Hashem. And part of what תוספות Tosafot says is is
that we call the תפילין tfillin, תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei kedusha, not קדושה
עצמה. kedusha atzma. And if we really thought that this was forming
שם השם, shem Hashem, it wouldn't just be serving the קלפים klafim
and תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei kedusha, it would be actual קדושה kedusha itself.
So תוספות Tosafot downplays the emphasizing of the forming, I mean, which
doesn't mean he disagrees that that's how you make the knot, but
just it doesn't have a halachic status of
שם השם.
shem Hashem. And no more holy than a מזוזה mezuzah case? No,
no, no, because the מזוזה mezuzah is תשמישי דתשמישי.
tashmishei d'tashmishei. The תפילין tefillin are serving the קלפים, klafim, the case
is serving the תפילין tefillin which are serving the קלפים. klafim. Are
they no more holy than let's say like the like the what
do you call it, like the what's it called, the mantle that
you put on the ספר תורה? sefer torah? Like that would be
the better comparison, it's directly being משמש meshaimesh כתבי קודש. kisvei kodesh.
And the answer might be that in terms of its קדושה no,
but it's also תשמישי מצוה. tashmishei mitzvah, A תפילין tefillin is two
things, תשמישי מצוה, tashmishei mitzvah it's a מצוה mitzvah object, and it's
serving the קלפים, klafim, it's תשמישי קדושה. tashmishei kedusha. Okay, but תוספות
Tosafot says קדושה עצמה, kedusha atzma, what's not really שם השם shem
Hashem written on the תפילין. tefillin? Okay, on the actual leather of
the תפילין.
tefillin. You see the ד dalet but of course the same shape
makes the י. yud. What? The knot.
You see the ד dalet but with the same shape as a
י. yud.
Well the י yud on your, you mean the ד dalet is
more or less looks like a י. yud.
No, the knot is also a י. yud.
No the י yud the the knot on the של יד shel
yad is the י. yud. Oh, I can see. You're saying they
basically look the same. No, the the knot of the של יד
shel yad is very different than the knot on the של ראש.
shel rosh Now if you wanted to say that neither looks too
much like either letter, that's what תוספות Tosafot. says. Don't tell me
this is a real letter, okay? But at least the של יד
shel yad and the של ראש shel rosh... are made different. Now
תוספות Tosafot has a fascinating idea about this is. We treat the
תפילין tefillin exactly like this. What, you're telling me like it's no
different than the mantle of a ספר Sefer תורה? Torah I want
to show you an amazing, I know we're getting late but an
amazing line in תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot again, this אלו תפילין שבראש,
elu tfillin she'be'rosh, about four lines before the line get wide, last
two words of the line, תוספות Tosafot says the following. He says
הרב יעקב דאורלינש מסתפק, Harav Yaakov d'Orleans mistapek, so not New Orleans,
Orleans, was doubted, had a question if צריך לחלוץ תפילין של יד
כשנכנס לבית הכיסא. tzarich lachlotz tfillin shel yad k'shenichnas l'beis hakise. You're
going to the bathroom do you have to take off your של
ראש... shel rosh של יד? shel yad? דשמא כיון דמחופה עור לא
צריך. d'shema kivan d'michupa or lo tzarich. It's covered with leather. Now
what's covered with leather? Not the boxes, the parchment is covered with
leather. The parchment is what's a problem of bringing into the בית
הכיסא. beis hakise. Halachically you're allowed to walk with your מזוזה mezuzah
into the beis, not your מזוזה, mezuzah, your לולב into the בית
הכיסא. beis hakise. Not only that, every single time you go into
the בית הכיסא beis hakise you walk with תשמישי מצוה tashmishei mitzvah
into it. Your ציצית. So you can walk with תשמישי מצוה tashmishei
mitzvah, into the בית הכיסא, beis hakise, you can't walk with the
parchment. Wait a minute, but the question is maybe they're covered with
leather, it's not a problem. So why is the של ראש shel
rosh different? And then he says דלא אסרו אלא
תפילין של ראש שכתוב שין בעור. d'lo asru ela tfillin shel rosh
she'kasuv shin ba'or. So maybe that ש shin makes the של ראש
shel rosh, a quasi like כיסוי הקודש kisoi hakodesh itself. It has
part of שם השם shem Hashem or a letter that represents שם
השם. shem Hashem. So here, so right, so A, that might be
a different voice than the one he was saying before, but even
if he denies that you have real ש shin ד dalet י,
yud, he might admit that at least the ש shin gives it
some weight. So here you actually have a really like, you know,
here David, what is this thing of תפילין, tefillin I'm not sure
if this answers your question. There's a halachic answer, it's not a
philosophical answer, but anyway it's both תשמישי מצוה, tashmishei mitzvah right, which
is like ציצית,
and it's תשמישי קדושה tashmishei kedusha because it's serving the קלפים klafim
מצד mitzad is it קדושה עצמה, kedusha atzma, well maybe the ש,
shin, maybe the של ראש, shel rosh that we can talk about.
To the point that תוספות Tosafot thinks if ושל יד v'shel yad
which is only תשמישי קדושה tashmishei kedusha and תשמישי מצוה tashmishei mitzvah.
but the actual כיסוי הקודש kisoi hakodesh that themselves are covered, maybe
you can walk with your של יד shel yad into the bathroom.
And maybe it's only a problem with the של ראש shel rosh,
which actually has that exposed ש. shin.
Does the box cover or?
No the actual,
neither, the actual leather box itself covers the קלפים. klafim.
As the של יד shel yad is covered.
Yeah, but no no no, but but he's saying the קלפים klafim
inside the בית bayit are covered. And the קלפים klafim are the
only thing you're really not allowed to bring into the בית הכיסא.
beis hakise. Okay?
You said before that the the cover, yeah, but that's not what
תוספות Tosafot is talking about, right?
But an anthropologist might say that it's easier to take off the
של ראש, shel rosh. it's more difficult to take off the של
יד shel yad and reason to go to the bathroom with ארבע
כנפות arba kanfos and don't with a טלית.
tallis. Interesting. But you could go in with a טלית. tallis. Yeah,
but his point is that maybe they maybe they... Maybe that informs
one another as well, right? For example also you know what else
you don't go into? You don't go into do you know we
say you're not supposed to go into the bathroom with like a
קיטל kittel like if you're wearing it on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
Why? Because they say well because it's a בגד מיוחד לתפילה. beged
miyuchad l'tefillah. Now I don't know I'm about to wear my קיטל
kittel at the סדר Seder night so it's not so מיוחד לתפילה
miyuchad l'tefillah but anyway but it also had to do with some
of this issue about well okay and also you can take it
off. It's easy to take off. So alright so anyway there you
have a very interesting discussion about the weight of שם השם Shem
Hashem on the actual boxes itself and the idea of תפילין tefillin
as תשמישי קדושה tashmishei kedushah or תשמישי מצוה. mitzvah. Okay so let's
continue.
A little more
אגדתא. Agadata. בואו נראה. Bo nireh. תניא, Tanya, we taught: רבי אליעזר
הגדול אומר, Rabbi Eliezer haGadol omer, "והסירותי את כפי וראית את אחורי".
V'hasiroti et kapi v'raita et achorai. God says to משה, Moshe, "I
will remove my hand and you'll see my back." So אמר רב
כהנא בר ביזנא אמר רבי שמעון חסידא, Amar Rav Kahana bar Bizna
amar Rabbi Shimon Chasida, מלמד שהראה לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה קשר
של תפילין. melamed she'herah lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu l'Moshe kesher shel tefillin.
So what's the back of God? Back of God's head? Well what
do you see? You see the קשר kesher of the תפילין tefillin?
because God wears תפילין tefillin which is a famous גמרא Gemara in
ברכות. Berachot. I did not have enough time to give some to
come up with some profound explanation for this but the idea of
all the things that משה Moshe sees is the קשר של תפילין.
kesher shel tefillin. You imagine the גמרא Gemara is not just pointing
out well sort of like what you know what happens to be
at the back of God's head but there's some significance about that
קשר של תפילין kesher shel tefillin but right now I don't have
it.
In משה's Moshe time?
What? תפילין? tefillin What משה? Moshe? God commanded it in the תורה
Torah so presumably yes and then the גמרא Gemara understands that even
God wears תפילין.
tefillin Because the Jews didn't pray before the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
You don't have to wear תפילין tefillin when you pray, you wear
תפילין tefillin. whatever. It's the whole day. The תורה Torah doesn't say
you wear it when you pray.
Only to put it on.
Put it on, take it off, say שמע, Shema, I don't know.
The גמרא Gemara doesn't say anything about taking it off. They used
to wear it the whole day, right? Well that's a question whether
they actually did it. In theory you're supposed to, whether they actually
did it is another question. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, קשר של תפילין צריך שיהא למעלה
כדי שישראל יהיו למעלה. kesher shel tefillin tzarich she'yehei l'ma'alah kedei she'Yisrael
yihiyu l'ma'alah. It should be above which basically means you know not
like at the back not below like below your hairline at the
sort of close to the shoulder but actually what is called the
nape of the neck. Yeah so actually where we put it is
where you can feel the bottom of the bone before there's like
a little indent here in the back of your neck. Right the
bottom of your skull but it's high you know not at the
very low part of the neck. Why? כדי שישראל יהיו למעלה ולא
למטה. kedei she'Yisrael yihiyu l'ma'alah v'lo l'mata. That Israel should be above
and not below. Now again that's pretty bizarre. So is it פסול
pasul if I do it otherwise? I mean that's a nice little
דרוש, drash, you know what is he saying? Like there should be
nice symbolism or is he saying no this is a real הלכה
halacha and now let me give you a little דרוש? drash? Again
not clear. I wanted to say something too about the ישראל למעלה
ולא למטה Yisrael l'ma'alah v'lo l'mata which does tie into the קשר
של תפילין kesher shel tefillin because the גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachot
that talks about God wearing תפילין tefillin says what's written in God's
תפילין? tefillin, Does anybody remember what the גמרא Gemara says? מי כעמך
ישראל גוי אחד בארץ. Mi k'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz. So the
same way our תפילין Tefillin, speak about our holding God up high
and recognizing God above us, in a way God's תפילין Tefillin, are
expressive of His relationship with בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So the idea
ישראל Yisrael should be למעלה ולא למטה l'ma'alah v'lo l'mata is not
that we should be our you know we should be thinking about
God and God should be above, ישראל למעלה ולא למטה Yisrael l'ma'alah
v'lo l'mata is I think directly in the context of the מדרש
midrash I just said before about the קשר של תפילין. kesher shel
tefillin. If you want that's the most I could say about what
it means that God, משה Moshe saw the back of God. The
רמב"ם, Rambam, seeing this רמב"ם Rambam says what does it mean? The
רמב"ם Rambam of course always very bothered with the anthropomorphisms. What does
God mean when He says to the רמב"ם Rambam when He says
to... that's a good question. What does God mean when He says
to משה Moshe you'll see my you'll see my back and not
my front? So God says it means you can't truly understand what
I God am but you can see how I act in the
world and you can sort of see my if you were my
my ways, my you know my echo of my presence and that's
my back. So in a way if the תפילין Tefillin, are מי
כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ Mi k'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz and
it talks about God's relationship to בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, so seeing
the קשר של תפילין kesher shel tefillin is somehow seeing you
know the how God acts within history and in terms of God's
relationship to ישראל. Yisrael.
They're guessing on God's תפילין Tefillin down there right now.
You
know they also they
also don't know that God wears תפילין. Tefillin? What does the whole
thing mean anyway?
What are you tying into?
You know I think we have to open up God's תפילין Tefillin,
and see if He פוסק paskens like רש"י Rashi or רבינו תם
Rabbeinu Tam. which was what we read yesterday about the שדר מן
השמיים. shedar min ha-shamayim. Alright then now the גמרא Gemara,
says like this, I have something else in the גמרא Gemara about
that the תפילין, Tefillin. the פרשיות parshiyot are covered. This idea that
you know the the reader that to the right of the reader
or the left of the reader. Right, you can't read them, they're
in a box and then the way you're wearing them connect...
Oh, you mean that קשר kesher is the only thing you can
see.
Yeah, maybe this...
Oh, the same way the שין shin is a part that you
can actually see so there's that power there, right, right. I did
want to also mention I know we're falling further behind, yeah the
שין shin in the גמרא Gemara just says the שין, shin, תוספות
Tosafot there quotes the שימוש רבא. Shimusha Rabba. We won't read it
inside but on the previous דף daf. again this ספר שימוש רבא
Sefer Shimusha Rabba that speaks about having a one side having a
three armed שין shin and the other having a four armed שין
shin and that's what we do although again like now... not in
the גמרא, Gemara it's from the ספר called the שימושא רבא, Shimusha
Rabba, but again he was probably reflecting what practices were, and some
say that the point about the four-armed שין Shin is that it
almost like
no, well, maybe, they represent the four פרשיות, Parshiyot, also
that it represents the space between those arms, you know, you can
fit upside down into a four-arm שין, Shin, a three-arm שין. Shin.
If you imagine this created, right, if you imagine the white space
here, an upside down white space of a three-leg שין, Shin, you
know, fits into a four-leg שין, Shin, and that actually is what
תוספות Tosafot says, and that part of that has to do with
the idea again about like, you know, is it, you know, makes
you think about the sort of לוחות Luchot that God gave, the
space as opposed to the, you know, that they were formed, the
letters were formed by cutting through in the space, and how much
is it sort of, you know, the word what we're seeing or
what God is seeing,
I don't know, maybe
the three-armed, maybe the
four-leg Shin? Who's to say that with a modern Hebrew, could that
have been the cuneiform?
Could have been, but we're writing it in אשורית Ashurit Hebrew, so,
oh
well, אש לבנה Esh Levanah maybe?
That's my point.
Wow. Oh, the black, oh, and this is the אש לבנה, Esh
Levanah, so there's what to do with, why do
we care that a three-arm שין? Shin?
I don't know why we care. Somehow had to do something with,
I really don't know why we care. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara. says, so moving
on, where were we? Okay, וצריך שיהא כלפי פנים כדי שיהא ישראל
לפנים ולא לאחור. V’tzarich sheyehei klapei panim kedei sheyehei Yisrael lifnim velo
l’achor. It had to be facing front, that whatever facing front means
is a little unclear. We're back to the קשר של תפילין, Kesher
shel Tefillin, and רש''י Rashi says what it means
is that it probably just means the black is on the outside
and the white is on the inside, it has to be facing
properly, that Israel should be in front and not behind. אמר רב
שמואל בר בי רב יהודה אמר רב ואמרי לה אמר רב אחא
אריכא אמר רב הונא ואמרי לה אמר רב מנשיא אמר שמואל תפילין
מאימתי מברך עליהם. Amar Rav Shmuel bar bei Rav Yehuda amar Rav
v’amri lah amar Rav Acha Aricha amar Rav Huna v’amri lah amar
Rav Menashya amar Shmuel Tefillin me’imatai mevarech aleihem. Okay, moving on. Now
he's got the physical boxes of the תפילין, Tefillin. okay, and now
we have the question about putting them on. When do you make
the ברכה? Berakha? So משעת הנחתן, mishat hanachatan, from the moment that
you place it on. So the גמרא Gemara says איני, eini, is
that really true? והאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל כל מצות כולן מברך
עליהן עובר לעשייתן, veha’amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel kol mitzvot kulan mevarech
aleihen over la’asiyatan, before you do it? משעת הנחתן mishat hanachatan sounds
like you already put it on.
אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו משעת הנחה ועד שעת קשירה. Abaye v’Rava de’amri
tarvaihu mishat hanacha v’ad she’at keshira. No, we mean you place it
on your hand, you make the ברכה, Berakha, or you place it
on your head, you make the ברכה, Berakha, and then you tighten
it, then you do the קשירה, keshira so you do it right
before you do it. We don't mean after you place it on,
we mean between the time when it's ready to go on and
then the ברכה Berakha and then the actual tightening. Now the גמרא
Gemara says here עד שעת קשירה. ad she’at keshira. There's a very
interesting תוספות Tosafot that says takes the word קשירה keshira literally and
says that what this means is, I'll just give you the first
line, משעת הנחה ועד שעת קשירה, mishat hanacha v’ad she’at keshira, מכאן
היה מדקדק רבינו אליהו שצריך אדם לקשור תפילין בכל יום, mikan haya
medakdek Rabbeinu Eliyahu shetzarich adam likshor Tefillin bechol yom, that you do
not just tighten your תפילין, Tefillin, that you come every morning, you
got to come earlier to שול, shul, and basically you take you
have your box, you have your strap, and you start making the
loops and making the knots and doing the whole thing and actually
tightening and making it, and then he says probably maybe that's only
on the של יד shel yad and not the של ראש. shel
rosh, But you can imagine what that would be, you're actually doing
the קשר, kesher, not just the tightening. Partly though, why does תוספות
Tosafot say this? He says because we got a פסוק, Pasuk, that's
how he reads קשירה keshira in the גמרא. Gemara And then he
says no, קשירה keshira is לאו דוקא, lav davka, קשירה keshira means
tightening not knotting. But תוספות Tosafot says I have a פסוק, Pasuk,
right? What does the פסוק Pasuk say? He says if you take
a look, תוספות Tosafot says like this,
he says
at the top of ל''ו ע''א, lamed vav amud aleph, תוספות Tosafot
says like this,
ומסתברא, u’mistabra, one, two, three, three lines down in the narrow lines,
middle of lines,
ומסתברא כדברי רבינו תם בתפילין של ראש, u’mistabra kedivrei Rabbeinu Tam bi’Tefillin
shel rosh, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says you don't have to make
the קשר, kesher, that's on the תפילין של ראש, Tefillin shel rosh,
וכדברי רבינו אליהו בתפילין של יד, uk’divrei Rabbeinu Eliyahu bi’Tefillin shel yad,
why? כדכתיב בשל יד וקשרתם לאות על ידך, kedichtiv bishel yad u’kshartam
l’ot al yadecha, דמשמע דכל שעה שקשור צריך קשירה, demashma dechol sha’a
shekshur tzarich keshira, you gotta make a knot, you gotta love a
mapping of a straight פסוק. Pasuk. Okay? The פסוק Pasuk says make
a knot, so therefore maybe by the של יד shel yad you
actually need to make a knot. Now, of course, תוספות Tosafot says
it's pretty funny in the immediate context of having learned about מזוזה,
Mezuzah, where it says וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך, uch’tavtam al mezuzot beitecha,
and you actually don't take out your quill and start writing, right?
So his point is, you know, you made a קשירה kshira and
now by having it is doing the מצוה, mitzvah. but תוספות Tosafot
wants to say maybe we read this literally. And maybe, David, your
point I was also thinking about, the ontological point, it's a lot
easier to make this like loop thing of the של יד shel
yad than it is to make this complicated knot of the של
ראש, shel rosh. at least the way we make the knot of
the של ראש. shel rosh. So it also, you know, allowed for
oh
you already had a loop that you're tightening. What? Yeah, you already
had a loop that you are,
yeah I know, but רבינו אליהו Rabbeinu Eliyahu says that doesn't count.
You have to actually put the strap into the תפילין, Tefillin make
the loop, make the knot. Or he doesn't mean the י', Yud,
making the י' Yud on there? Does he make that every day?
I don't think so, I think he means putting the strap into
the תפילין Tefillin and connecting. Now, of course, it's a little funny
because וקשרתם, Ukshartem does that mean you should make a knot on
your תפילין? tefillin, It means you should you should bind your תפילין,
tefillin not your תפילין. tefillin: But maybe this is that what you
do the whole knotting? You put the whole loop in, you do
the whole binding, not just the tightening. So anyway it's hard to
understand like why that פסוק pasuk is so compelling since it's really
about connecting it to your arm, which is what we do do.
But what it does point to, and we will see this in
a minute when we get to the different ברכות brachot you make,
is the different verbs that the תורה uses. A more active verb
by the של יד shel yad and a more static verb by
the של ראש. shel rosh,
וקשרתם ukshartem, as opposed to והיו. vehayu. So תוספות Tosafot are thinking
it might make a difference whether you have to actually make the
knot or not. Let's keep on going as the גמרא Gemara talks
about the specific ברכות brachot that you make.
תוספות Tosafot would be
right, tightening it in not every day?
וליף רבינו אליהו V'alif rivieno Eliyahu would. אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav
Chisda. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, סח בין תפילה לתפילה חוזר
ומברך. Sach bein tefillah l'tefillah chozer u'mevarech. If somebody talks between the
תפילין של יד Tefillin shel yad and the תפילין של ראש, Tefillin
shel rosh, we normally are not used to seeing these words in
the singular. It does not here mean a prayer. If you talk
between the של יד shel yad and the של ראש, shel rosh,
you have to go and make another ברכה. bracha. Now the גמרא
Gemara? says, well what does that mean? סח Sach in only if
he spoke, you did a הפסק, hefsek, לא סח lo sach not
if he didn't. והא שלח רבי חייא בריה דרב הונא משמיה דרבי
יוחנן. Veha shalach Rabi Chiya breih d'Rav Huna mishmei d'Rabi Yochanan. We
have a letter sent in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan
from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael on תפילה של יד אומר ברוך אשר
קדשנו במצותיו וצונו להניח תפילין. Al tefillah shel yad omer Baruch asher
kideshanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu lehaniach Tefillin. On the תפילין של יד Tefillin shel
yad you say אשר קדשנו להניח. asher kideshanu lehaniach. על של ראש,
Al shel rosh, on the תפילין של ראש Tefillin shel rosh what
do you say? ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על מצות תפילין. Baruch
asher kideshanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu al mitzvat Tefillin. Okay. Now before we get
to how this is relevant to one ברכה bracha or two ברכות,
brachot, which it obviously is, the question is what's the different נוסח?
nosach? So רש"י Rashi says the different נוסח nosach is ל Lamed
is imperfect. It means you're not done yet. So you're still in
the process of להיות מניח. lihyot meniach. על מצות Al mitzvat is
when you have the של ראש, shel rosh it's all done. So
now you can talk, the מצוה mitzvah, was completed. But I understand,
not not me, others say greater and you know much greater than
I have pointed out that the difference is exactly reflecting the פסוקים.
psukim. That the
וקשרתם לאות ukshartem l'ot is an active verb, so you say להניח,
lehaniach, that it's to do an act to put on the תפילין.
Tfillin. The של ראש shel rosh is a static verb, והיו לטטפת,
vehayu l'totafot, על מצות, al mitzvat, on the status of תפילין, tfillin,
on the מצוה. mitzvah The מצוה mitzvah. is complete, but it's not
about an action of doing, it's about having the תפילין tfillin, on
me. So two ways of understanding the different נוסח הברכה. nosach habracha.
And what we see is there are two ברכות. brachot. So why
did we say only if you spoke between the two do you
make a second ברכה? bracha? Here we say you anyway make a
second ברכה. bracha. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara, answers.
אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו. Abaye v'Rava d'amri tarveihu. They both say לא
סח מברך אחת סח מברך שתים. lo sach mevarech achat sach mevarech
shtayim. Okay, if you didn't talk you only make one ברכה, bracha,
if you talk you make two. So the פשט pshat of this
גמרא Gemara is that if you don't talk you just make one
ברכה bracha on both of them, and that was his statement of
if you talk you have to make another, if you don't talk
you just make one ברכה. bracha. When we said there are two
different ברכות, brachot, that happens, that's what happens if you do talk.
If you do talk then you make two different ברכות, brachot, although
he didn't say that. That is what רש"י Rashi says. That is
מן הסברא. min hasvara. מן הסברא Min hasvara is that they do
not, they only make one ברכה bracha on תפילין tfillin, unless for
some reason they don't have
their של... shel? you know, there was some הפסק hefsek. between the
two of them. מנהג אשכנז, Minhag Ashkenaz, what?
להניח. Lehaniach. Okay. Um, only if it's an הפסק. hefsek Now basically
it's one, you conceptualize it as although it's true אין מעכבין זה
את זה, ein me'akvin zeh et zeh, which we haven't gotten to
yet, and you can do של יד shel yad without של ראש
shel rosh. or whatever. When they come together they form a larger
complete process and it's one complete מצוה. mitzvah So one ברכה bracha
goes on both sides. תוספות Tosafot raises interesting questions. We're back to
do בדיקת חמץ. bedikat chametz. We don't have time, I can't go
into this. תוספות Tosafot asks what happens when you're מפסיק mafsik other
things which are processes? Do you have to make another ברכה? bracha?
So there's one thing like בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz which is clearly
one thing, one process, not multiple little things. There are other things
which are much more clearly very distinct things that I'm doing all
at the same
sequentially. Talks about שחיטה. shechita. I have a thousand chickens that I'm
going to שחט. shacht. I say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על השחיטה
asher kideshanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu al hashechita and I start שחיטה. shechting. I
don't make it before each one. What happens if I'm מפסיק? mafsik?
There clearly they're different acts that are just happening in sequence. And
then you have our case which is somewhere in between. Because on
the one hand you don't, if you do יד yad without ראש
rosh or ראש rosh. without יד yad you're יוצא. yotzei. They're not
like בדיקת חמץ, bedikat chametz, it's all one thing conceptually. But on
the other hand it's not like שחיטה shechting a lot of chickens,
they combine to form a larger מצוה. mitzvah, So what constitutes the
הפסק hefsek could be different in all those three scenarios, you know,
because you're trying to get your ברכה bracha to go on multiple
things or on one thing and so on. So that's one question
about what constitutes the הפסק about talking. I want to though talk
about the importance of the difference between the ספרדים Sefardim and the
אשכנזים Ashkenazim question about the ברכה bracha that you make. Because if
you make basically the ברכה, bracha, like, oh, I didn't say, did
I say the other read of the גמרא? Gemara The other read
of the גמרא, Gemara which תוספות Tosafot says is, if you're לא
סח, lo sach, we're talking about the של ראש. shel rosh, You
always make a ברכה bracha on the של יד, shel yad, אשר
קדשנו במצותיו וצונו להניח תפילין. asher kideshanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu lehaniach Tefillin. Now
when it talks about the ברכה bracha on the של ראש, shel
rosh and you always make the ברכה bracha of על מצות תפילין
al mitzvat Tefillin like רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan sent, that's true, you
always make those two ברכות. brachot. When does סח sach matter? About
whether the של ראש shel rosh. is going to get just one
ברכה bracha or two ברכות. brachot. So if I talk between
the של יד shel yad and the של ראש. shel rosh. That
we do one on the של יד shel yad and one on
the של ראש. shel rosh. If you talk and you מפסיק, mafsik,
you make two on the של ראש. shel rosh By the way,
there are cases where this is הלכה למעשה, halacha lema'aseh, I mean
besides if you talk. For example, let's say somebody can't put on
a של יד, shel yad, somebody has a cast or whatever reason
there is a חציצה chatzitza or doesn't have an arm, right? What
do you do? So they are separate מצוות mitzvot. and you would
put on the של ראש shel rosh and you'd make both ברכות.
brachot. Okay? So that's the way for the ספרדים Sefardim you'd make
the one ברכה. bracha. So that's the difference. So both אשכנזים Ashkenazim
and ספרדים Sefardim do agree that if you're not סח, sach, the
ברכה bracha on the של יד shel yad goes on the של
ראש shel rosh and we see it as like one larger מצווה,
mitzva, one larger process. If you do סח sach then you have
to look at it as a separate מצווה mitzva and therefore it
gets its ברכה. bracha. The debate is whether you always also acknowledge
the של ראש shel rosh as something distinct. If you whether the
אשכנזים Ashkenazim always acknowledge, you know you have like both things going
on, each thing retains its distinct identity and it's part of a
process. That's the way I would say, you know, part of a
whole, that's I would say the אשכנזי Ashkenazi way. להניח, lehaniach, על
מצוות, al mitzvat, each one separate. On the other hand, they are
all, you know, they're also parts of the להניח lehaniach has to
go on the של ראש shel rosh, as well. Or the way
the ספרדים Sefardim say it is that no, if you know if
you don't have a need to single out the status of the
של ראש, shel rosh, you don't and it's one ברכה bracha on
all. The other interesting thing to note is where both אשכנזים Ashkenazim
and ספרדים Sefardim both agree that the ברכה bracha of להניח lehaniach
goes on the של ראש, shel rosh which is again interesting.
על מצוות al mitzvat you mean? No, להניח.
lehaniach. When you say להניח lehaniach that also relates, it covers the
של ראש shel rosh, and the evidence is that when you're מפסיק,
mafsik, now you have to make a separate להניח lehaniach on the
של ראש, shel rosh. both for אשכנזים Ashkenazim and... well no, for
the ספרדים Sefardim actually it becomes a על מצוות. al mitzvat.
רבותי, rabbotai, and if you talk for the ספרדים, Sefardim, what happens?
Then you have to make it על מצוות תפילין al mitzvat tfillin
on the של ראש. shel rosh? And להניח lehaniach again or not?
No. Anyway, without talking, it's getting a little complicated, we need to
move on but the point I just want to make is thinking
about how much again going back to the פסוק pasuk of וקשרתם,
ukshartem how much is the idea of an action of binding a
concept that applies to the של ראש? shel rosh, Okay, and for
the אשכנזים Ashkenazim you actually, you know, if you don't have your
של יד, shel yad, you're going to say two ברכות brachot on
the של ראש, shel rosh להניח lehaniach and על מצוות. al mitzvat.
That shows that even for the אשכנזים Ashkenazim just the של ראש
shel rosh by itself, or should talk, the של ראש shel rosh
right itself, the concept
of an action of putting on applies. For the ספרדים Sefardim it's
less clear because if you just have the של ראש shel rosh
by itself you do על מצוות. al mitzvat. And when you have
both you do להניח lehaniach but your primary focus then is on
the של יד. shel yad. So you never have a להניח lehaniach
focused on the של ראש shel rosh for the ספרדים. Sefardim. So
the point I want to get out of all of this is
going back to that תוספות Tosafot. about the about the language in
the פסוק pasuk is how much is the של ראש shel rosh
basically a static and how much is there a concept of an
action of putting it on? We saw as back תוספות Tosafot about
the קשירה kshira but it's also a question about the נוסח הברכה
nusach habracha and might break down to the ספרדי Sefardi אשכנזי Ashkenazi
position. Okay, but again for the אשכנזים Ashkenazim you always will make
a separate ברכה bracha as we know on the של ראש shel
rosh and for the ספרדים Sefardim only if you're מפסיק mafsik between
the two.
That would mean two ברכות brachot about the act of של?
Well again, that's the point I said, these are separate מצוות.
mitzvos, מעשה.
ma'aseh. Doing them now.
פסח. Pesach. When you say מוציא, motzei,
these are two ברכות המצווה birchot hamitzva is what he's saying according
to the אשכנזים. Ashkenazim. There's a ברכות הנהנין birchot hanehenin and a
ברכות המצווה. birchot hamitzva. What you're saying is that it's a two
ברכות המצווה, birchot hamitzva, which you're right, is a funny idea according
to the אשכנזי Ashkenazi thing, according to the אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach. But
it maybe points out to two dimensions of their מצווה. mitzva. There's
a מצווה mitzva to do the act of putting it on and
then there's a מצווה mitzva to have it on you. That's the
וקשרתם והיו. vehayu. But still you're right, since when do even if
a מצווה mitzva is complex and it has two dimensions, since when
would we make two ברכות המצווה? birchot hamitzva?
Is it maybe similar to what you were saying before how there's
two elements of קדושה, there's a...
Oh, I don't see it that way. I see it related to
whether to put it on or to have it on.
Wouldn't you expect that the ברכה bracha would be לקשר תפילין? lekashair
tfillin? Instead of להניח. lehaniach.
So that's a very good question and you know if anything it's
a good challenge to the רבינו אליהו Rabbeinu Eliyahu and תוספות. Tosafot
Maybe we specifically did not say לקשר lekashair because we don't actually
make the קשר. kesher. We put it on ourselves. So it's a
really strong question. I mean I hadn't connected it that way. But
you're right, according to him what would the נוסח הברכה nusach habracha
be here? Why not say לקשר? lekashair? Right.
But we could make it on the יד yad, and
call what we're doing a קשר. kesher. Right. It's a good point.
Is ברכת התורה birchat hatorah a ברכה ארוכה bracha arucha or or
two different ברכות? brachot? Well, that's a good point, you know, ברכת
התורה birchat hatorah is a good example.
And ברכת התורה birchat hatorah might be a hybrid of a ברכות
המצווה birchat hamitzva
אשר קדשנו asher kidshanu and a ברכת השבח birchat hashevach אשר בחר
בנו מכל העמים. asher bachar banu mikol ha'amim. But there are מחלוקות
machlokot about whether we predominantly look at ברכת התורה birchat hatorah as
predominantly a ברכות המצווה birchat hamitzva or predominantly a ברכת השבח. birchat
hashevach. So that's a good example where you have multiple dimensions being
reflected in multiple ברכות. brachot. Deem's point is still good that I
don't know of any other case that you have two אשר קדשנוs
asher kidshanu on one מעשה מצווה. ma'aseh mitzva. And even if we
can argue that it's a מעשה מצווה ma'aseh mitzva that has two
dimensions to it, which is
so maybe that's part of the problem with why the... like why
the ספרדים Sefardim don't like the אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach, you know, that
they say in principle the של ראש shel rosh, requires two ברכת
המצוה birchas hamitzvah is an idea they're not ready to embrace.
Only have the head, they only say
ברוך אתה Baruch atah להניח. l'haniach. I mean, על מצות... al mitzvas...
על מצוה. al mitzvah. They will never say להניח l'haniach on the
head. They'll say להניח l'haniach on the יד, yad which also goes
on the head, and they'll say על מצוה al mitzvah on a
separate one on the head. Talked. Right. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: All right, so תנא, tana, we תנא בריתא:
tana b'raisa: שח בין תפילה לתפילה, sach bein tefillah l'tefillah, if somebody
talks between the two תפילין, tfillin, עבירה היא בידו, aveirah hi b'yado,
it's a sin, וחוזר עליה מערכי מלחמה. v'chozer aleha m'orchei milchama. And
if you're going out to war, right, so you know it says
מי האיש הירא ורך הלבב, mi ha'ish ha'yarei v'rach ha'leivav, so the
גמרא says that means רך הלבב מן העבירה שבידו. rach ha'leivav min
ha'aveirah she'b'yado. So even if you just talk between the של יד
shel yad and the של ראש, shel rosh, that's a reason to
go back. Which is to impress us with how weighty the עבירה
aveirah is, or is it the opposite? It's a very small עבירה,
aveirah, but the point is you can go back for war even
for the most smallest of the sins. Not exactly clear. It seems
like it's more of the former. Yeah, so רש"י Rashi says it
means you talked between the two and you didn't make the right
ברכה bracha afterwards. Because if you do say the ברכה... bracha... but
I would say this is an important question, which is not clear:
Is the problem of talking just the problem of
requiring a ברכה שאינה צריכה?
bracha she'eina tzricha? תוספות Tosafot gets into a whole discussion of how
big of a problem is the idea of ברכה שאינה צריכה. bracha
she'eina tzricha. You know, so so what? So he talked and made
a ברכה. bracha. So says well, no, that's also an עבירה. aveirah.
You required a ברכה שאינה צריכה. bracha she'eina tzricha. You required another
ברכה. bracha. So רש"י and תוספות work with it within the context
of you didn't make the right ברכה bracha or you did a
ברכה שאינה צריכה bracha she'eina tzricha and so on. But the other
question is, going back to this idea that if we see these
as not two independent מצוות, mitzvos but as some joint, you know,
each one is independent, but they also are a joint larger מצוה,
mitzvah, and the evidence bringing that the ברכה bracha on the של
יד shel yad normally does apply to the של ראש, shel rosh
so maybe even if you do make the right ברכה, bracha, there's
an עבירה. aveirah. There's an עבירה aveirah of separating the מצוה of
תפילין tfillin as a separate של יד shel yad and של ראש
shel rosh. מצוה. The goal is to make it a unified process.
So even if you solve the ברכה bracha problem, you still have
separated the process. And the גמרא's not clear that the entire problem
here is the ברכה bracha problem. Okay, let's keep going a little
more. תנא, tana, we תנא בריתא: tana b'raisa: כשהוא מניח מניח של
יד ואחר כך מניח של ראש. k'she'hu meniach, meniach shel yad v'achar
kach meniach shel rosh. When you put it on, first you put
on the של יד shel yad and then the של ראש. shel
rosh וכשהוא חולץ חולץ של ראש ואחר כך חולץ של יד. uk'she'hu
choleitz, choleitz shel rosh v'achar kach choleitz shel yad. When you take
it off, you first take off the של ראש shel rosh. and
then the של יד. shel yad. Why is that? בשלמא כשהוא מניח
מניח של יד ואחר כך מניח של ראש, bishlama k'she'hu meniach, meniach
shel yad v'achar kach meniach shel rosh, I understand when you put
it on, first put on the יד and then the ראש. דכתיב
וקשרתם לאות על ידך והדר והיו לטטפות בין עיניך. dichviv ukshartem l'os
al yadecha v'hadar v'hayu l'totafos bein einecha. In order. Now, again, notice
the idea that we are treating this as one מצוה process. It's
not like you have two separate מצוות mitzvot to do. Here's the
process of putting two things on, which is the order that you
put them on. So again, this is sort of part of the
interesting thing about תפילין: tfillin. you can do one without the other,
but when you do both, it's part of one big complete larger
מצוה, which, as I said, is I think part of the problem
about שח, sach, not just the ברכה bracha problem. So I get
the order when you're putting it on. אלא כשהוא חולץ חולץ של
ראש ואחר כך חולץ של יד מנלן? ela k'she'hu choleitz, choleitz shel
rosh v'achar kach choleitz shel yad minalan? Who says that when you
reverse the order, I care which order you reverse it? So אמר
רבה ואמר רבה, amar Rabba v'amar Rabba, so רבה Rabba said, רב
הונא אסבר לי, Rav Huna asbar li, רב הונא Rav Huna explained
it to me: אמר קרא והיו לטטפות בין עיניך. amar kra v'hayu
l'totafos bein einecha. They shall be לטטפות, l'totafos, and והיו v'hayu is
plural. Okay, although טטפות totafos is also plural, here we're choosing to
read the word והיו v'hayu to refer both to the של יד
shel yad and the של ראש. shel rosh וקשרתם לאות והיו ukshartem
l'os v'hayu means the two of them shall be. So כל זמן
שבין עיניך יהיו שתים. kol zman she'bein einecha yehu shtayim. Whenever you
have the של ראש shel rosh and it's בין עיניך, bein einecha,
both of them should be on you. So the של ראש shel
rosh should be building on the של יד, shel yad, and therefore
you should not take off the של יד shel yad if you
would rip the foundation out from underneath. Okay, you have to build
so the של ראש shel rosh is only when there's also a
של יד shel yad and it builds on the של יד. shel
yad. Again showing somehow the dependency, not really halachically you can have
one without the other, but at least ideally the dependency of the
two and how they function together. I would also say what's fascinating
about this is again the difference of the action versus the status.
והיו, v'hayu, יהיו. yehiyu. So it's meaning the action is first do
A, then do B. Then the question is the state, what is
the state? So there's a state of being wearing both and the
idea of the של ראש shel rosh requires also the wearing of
the של יד shel yad and that's more about not the action
but about the state. So now when I'm taking it off, I
should not live in a state where I have the של ראש
on without the של יד. shel yad. תוספות says something similar. Yeah,
it says a separate מצוה, but it's also על מצות. al masos.
Like on פסח Pesach did they make both ברכות? brachos? That would
have been an interesting question. Right now nowadays we have only the
על אכילת מצה. al achilas matzah. If you had בזמן הפסח b'zman
haPesach would you say, so there is a נוסח nusach of a
ברכה: bracha: אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לאכול קרבן פסח עם מצות, asher
kideshanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu l'echol korban Pesach im matzos, you know, על מצות
ומרורים יאכלוהו. al matzos u'merorim yochluhu. When they said that, would they
also then say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על אכילת מצה? asher kideshanu
b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al achilas matzah? Why not? You know, but that is
a good example. I mean whether they would do that or not
I don't know, but that would be an example where you had
two very different roles of that. True. Let me just read the...
Let me just read to the bottom of the דף; we're already
late and I just want to finish to the bottom of the
דף. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: מאימתי נברך עליהן?
mei'ematai nevarech aleihen? תפילין. tfillin So תפילין, tfillin. מאימתי נברך עליהן, mei'ematai
nevarech aleihen, when you make the ברכה bracha on תפילין, tfillin משעת
הנחתן, mishat hanachatan, from the time you put them on. So in
a way we just had that, but now we're going to say
that it means also from the time that they're allowed to be
on, which means what? כל זמן, kol zman, היכא דמי? heicha dami?
היה משכים לצאת לדרך, haya mashkim latzet laderech, you woke up early
and you had to put on your תפילין, tfillin you didn't want
to carry them in your bag, you wanted to wear them, ומתיירא
שמא יאבדו, umityarei shema yovedu, you thought if you put them in
your knapsack they'd get lost or something, מניחן, menichan, put them on
now even though it's not yet daybreak, וכשיגיע זמן ממשמש בהן ומברך
עליהן. uch'sheyagia zman memashmesh bahen umevarech aleihen. And when the time comes,
then you touch them, you feel them, and you make a ברכה
bracha because the touching and the feeling, that's sort of like a
new placing on. Now, this is again a beautiful example of those
two definitions of קשירה kshira versus הנחה. hanacha. And notice how this
spills off of the phrase משעת הנחתן, mishat hanachatan, although before we
objected to the phrase and we said, "No, no, it means עד
שעת קשירה," ad shat kshira, but here we're actually, that the קשירה
kshira went before, the קשירה that's the real act, but if the
act of putting them on was done before the right time, before
daybreak, you can make the ברכה bracha as if you would, another
way to reframe the גמרא is you could make the ברכה bracha
כל זמן שמניחן, kol zman shemenichan, as long as you're still wearing
them, you can make the ברכה bracha because the importance is not
just the initial act, but the state of wearing. So therefore, okay,
but it's over for the next second you're about to wear it.
Okay, and therefore, so that is actually what we say, if you're
wearing ציצית from before, you feel your ציצית and you make the
ברכה, bracha, you feel your תפילין, tfillin so again what's very nice
about this is it's pointing again to the idea of the state
of wearing תפילין tfillin, and not just the act of putting on
תפילין. tfillin. And let's just finish this up. ועד מתי מניחן? v'ad
matai menichan? How long can you keep them on? עד שתשקע החמה,
ad shetishka hachama, until sunset. And there's two reasons why you don't
wear תפילין Tefillin at night. One is לילה לאו זמן תפילין, laila
lav zman tfillin, which is basically learning from the פסוקים psukim that
it says we'll see in a minute somehow that it's a דין
din of יום, yom, like a lot of other מצוות that apply
during the day. And the other is a concern that you'll fall
asleep and you'll pass gas and that's not keeping the קדושה of
the תפילין. Once it's sunset, right? Is there a Rabbeinu Tam for
a later time for that too? Meaning would Rabbeinu Tam agree that
like the second שקיעה? shkia? Yeah. Yeah. And I also think why
am I remembering that some people דוקא davka have a מנהג minhag
of putting on רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam תפילין after שקיעה shkia and
before צאת? tzait? Maybe because in הבית יוסף haBeis Yosef there's an
opinion. Maybe, but I also maybe it shouldn't be בל תוסיף bal
tosif side from, anyway, רבי יעקב אומר, Rabbi Yaakov omer, עד שתכלה
רגל מן השוק. ad shetichleh regel min hashuk. No, it's not just
after sunset, it's a חנוכה Chanukah דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. Right, after sunset until
everybody gets home because that's when people start getting ready for bed
and so on, so it's a clear concern, not of a הלכתי
halachic definition of לילה laila and יום, yom, it's not about a
פסוק, pasuk, it's about falling asleep. So as long as there's still
business on the street, we don't care. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, עד
זמן שינה. ad zman sheina. No, no, even if the people are
all home, until it's normally bedtime for you or for most people,
whatever, it's not an issue. So the last two opinions clearly are
a concern you'll fall asleep and pass gas, the first one sounds
like a more formalist approach that it's a concern of the definition
of night versus day. ומודים חכמים לרבי יעקב, umodim chachamim l'Rabbi Yaakov,
and חכמים Chachamim agree to רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, שאם חלצן she'im
chaltzan לצאת לבית הכסא או ליכנס לבית המרחץ, latzet l'beit hakisei o
leikanes l'beit hamerchatz, so here you get taking your תפילין off for
going to the bathroom, if you took them off ושקעה חמה v'shaka
chama and then it was sunset, so then they would agree שוב
אינו חוזר ומניחן, shuv eino chozer umenichan, you do not put them
back on. So they'll let you keep them on until it's time
where people fall asleep, but they won't לכתחילה lechatchila say you're allowed
to put them on. So the normal way of explaining this is
again, it's a concern of passing gas, it's a rabbinic concern, we
don't force people to take off תפילין until it's really a problematic
time, but לכתחילה lechatchila we would say don't put it on once
it is nightfall. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, and רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said, הלכה כרבי יעקב, halacha k'Rabbi Yaakov, the הלכה is
like רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, which is עד שתכלה רגל מן השוק,
ad shetichleh regel min hashuk, which basically means it's getting to be
after sunset but it's also getting to be that the business is
ending in the street and conceptually what that means is לילה laila
is זמן תפילין, zman tfillin, but it's a concern of falling asleep
and passing gas. I only remember it because of תכלה רגל מן
השוק. tichleh regel min hashuk. Yeah, right, when the stores close. Yeah.
Okay, right, depends if you live in Manhattan. Okay, רב חסדא ורבה
בר רב הונא, Rav Chisda v'Rabbah bar Rav Huna, so רב חסדא
Rav Chisda and רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna מצלו
בהו באורתא, matzlu behu b'orta, they davened while wearing תפילין, presumably they
davened מעריב Maariv while wearing תפילין. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, what does
באורתא b'orta mean? At night. Okay. Okay, whatever about that. איכא דאמרי,
Ika d'amri, some say, אין הלכה כרבי יעקב, ein halacha k'Rabbi Yaakov,
that we do not rule like רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov. So if
we don't rule like רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, what do you do
with, so then davening with them at night, before a minute ago
it was a support that you're allowed to keep them on after
sunset, but now if we don't rule like רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov
and if sunset you take them off, what were they doing wearing
them? ורב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא מצלו בהו באורתא, v'Rav Chisda
v'Rabbah bar Rav Huna matzlu behu b'orta, they did daven with them
at night. הוא פליגא. hu peliga. Okay, that was arguing. So fine,
there's a מחלוקת. machloket. They thought that you can wear them and
others think that you can't. So we are going to continue with
this tomorrow. We're still an עמוד behind, thankfully not more, about the
question about whether you can keep תפילין on at night or certainly
you can't put them on at night. Can you keep them on,
which is the question about whether לילה laila is לאו זמן תפילין
lav zman Tefillin which would require you to take it off or
whether it's a concern of falling asleep which would not require you
until it gets much later. To be continued tomorrow.